In this next set of
在接下来的视频中，(字幕翻译：仇利克，中国海洋大学)
videos, I would like to
我想
tell you about recommender systems.
讲一下推荐系统。
There are two reasons, I had
有两个原因，我想讲
two motivations for why I wanted to talk about recommender systems.
推荐系统有两个原因
The first is just that it
第一，仅仅因为它是
is an important application of machine learning.
机器学习中的一个重要的应用。
Over the last few years, occasionally I
在过去几年，我偶尔
visit different, you know, technology
访问硅谷不同的技术公司，
companies here in Silicon Valley
and I often talk to people
我常和工作在这儿
working on machine learning applications there
致力于机器学习应用的人们聊天，
and so I've asked
我常问
people what are the most
他们，最重要的
important applications of machine
机器学习的应用是什么，
learning or what are the machine
或者，你最想改进的
learning applications that you would most like to get
机器学习应用
an improvement in the performance of.
有哪些。
And one of the most frequent
我最常听到的
answers I heard was that
答案是
there are many groups out in Silicon
现在，在硅谷有很多团体
Valley now, trying to build better recommender systems.
试图建立很好的推荐系统。
So, if you think about
因此，如果你考虑
what the websites are
网站是什么
like Amazon, or what Netflix
像亚马逊，或网飞公司
or what eBay, or what
或易趣，或
iTunes Genius, made by Apple
iTunes Genius，苹果开发的，
does, there are many websites
有很多的网站
or systems that try to
或系统试图
recommend new products to use.
推荐新产品给用户。
So, Amazon recommends new books
因此，亚马逊推荐新书
to you, Netflix try to recommend
给你，网飞公司试图推荐
new movies to you, and so on.
新电影给你，等等。
And these sorts of recommender systems,
这些推荐系统，
that look at what books you
浏览你过去
may have purchased in the past,
买过什么书，
or what movies you have rated
或过去评价过什么电影，
in the past, but these are
但是，
the systems that are responsible
这些系统会带来
for today, a substantial fraction of
很大一部分收入
Amazon's revenue and for a
为亚马逊和
company like Netflix, the recommendations
像网飞这样的公司，
that they make to the users
给用户推荐的电影
is also responsible for a
也占据了
substantial fraction of the movies
用户所看电影的一大部分。
watched by their users.
And so an
因此，
improvement in performance of
对推荐系统性能的改善
a recommender system can have
a substantial and immediate
将对这些企业的
impact on the bottom line of
底线有实质性和直接的影响。
many of these
companies. Recommender systems is kind of a funny
推荐系统是个有趣的问题，
problem, within academic machine
在学术机器学习中
learning so that we could
因此，我们
go to an academic machine learning conference,
可以去参加一个学术机器学习会议，
the problem of recommender systems,
推荐系统问题
actually receives relatively little attention,
实际上受到很少的关注，
or at least it's sort of a smaller
或者，至少在学术界
fraction of what goes on within Academia.
它占了很小的份额。
But if you look at what's happening,
但是，如果你看正在发生的事情，
many technology companies, the ability
许多有能力构建这些系统的科技企业，
to build these systems seems to be a high priority for many companies.
他们似乎在很多企业中占据很高的优先级。
And that's one of the reasons why I want to talk about them in this class.
这是我为什么在这节课讨论它的原因之一。
The second reason that I
我想讨论推荐系统地第二个原因是
want to talk about recommender systems
is that as we approach
the last few sets of videos
这个班视频的最后几集
of this class I wanted to talk about
我想讨论
a few of the big ideas
机器学习中的一些大思想
in machine learning and share with you,
并和大家分享，
you know, some of the big ideas in machine learning.
你知道的，机器学习中的一些大思想。
And we've already seen
这节课我们也看到了，
in this class that features are
对机器学习来说，特征是
important for machine learning, the
很重要的，
features you choose will have
你所选择的特征
a big effect on the performance of your learning algorithm.
将对你学习算法的性能有很大的影响。
So there's this big idea in machine
因此，在机器学习中有一种大思想，
learning, which is that for
它针对一些问题，
some problems, maybe not
可能并不是
all problems, but some problems, there
所有的问题，而是一些问题，
are algorithms that can try
有算法可以为你
to automatically learn a good set of features for you.
自动学习一套好的特征。
So rather than trying to hand
因此，不要试图手动设计，
design, or hand code the
或手写代码
features, which is mostly what we've
这是目前为止我们常干的，
been doing so far, there are a
few settings where you might
有一些设置，你可以
be able to have an
有一个算法，
algorithm, just to learn what feature to
仅仅学习其使用的特征，
use, and the recommender
推荐系统
systems is just one example of that sort of setting.
就是类型设置的一个例子。
There are many others, but engraved
还有很多其它的，但是
through recommender systems, will be
通过推荐系统，我们将
able to go a little
领略一小部分
bit into this idea of learning
特征学习的思想，
the features and you'll be
至少，你将能够
able to see at least one example
了解到这方面的一个例子，
of this, I think, big idea in machine learning as well.
我认为，机器学习中的大思想也是这样。
So, without further ado, let's
因此，让我们
get started, and talk
开始讨论
about the recommender system problem formulation.
推荐系统问题公式化。
As my running example, I'm
接下来的例子，我将
going to use the
用
modern problem of predicting movie ratings.
电影评级预测现代问题。
So, here's a problem.
因此，这是一个问题。
Imagine that you're a
假设你是一个
website or a company that
网站或者公司
sells or rents out movies, or what have you.
出售或者出租电影，或者诸如此类。
And so, you know, Amazon, and Netflix, and
因此，你知道，亚马逊、网飞公司和
I think iTunes are all examples
iTunes都是做这个的
of companies that do this,
公司。
and let's say you let
比方说，你让
your users rate different movies,
你的用户评价不同的电影，
using a 1 to 5 star rating.
用1到5星级评价。
So, users may, you know,
因此，用户可能，你知道，
something one, two, three, four or five stars.
评定一星、二星、三星、四星或五星。
In order to make this example
为了让这个例子
just a little bit nicer, I'm
更完善一点，我
going to allow 0 to
将允许0到
5 stars as well,
5星级，
because that just makes some of the math come out just nicer.
这只是让数字呈现的更好一些。
Although most of these websites use the 1 to 5 star scale.
虽然大多数网站使用1到5星级评价。
So here, I have 5 movies.
这里，我有5部电影。
You know, Love That
你们知道的，Love That
Lasts, Romance Forever, Cute Puppies of
Love, Nonstop Car Chases,
and Swords vs. Karate.
And we have 4 users, which,
我们有4个用户，
calling, you know, Alice, Bob, Carol,
他们分别是Alice, Bob, Carol,
and Dave, with initials A, B,
和Dave,名字首字母分别是A, B,
C, and D, we'll call them users 1, 2, 3, and 4.
C和D,我们称呼他们用户1,2,3和用户4.
So, let's say Alice really
比如说Alice喜欢
likes Love That Lasts and
Love That Lasts并
rates that 5 stars, likes Romance
给其评价5星，Romance
Forever, rates it 5 stars.
Forever,评价5星。
She did not watch Cute Puppies
她并没有看过Cute Puppies
of Love, and did rate it, so we
of Love,没有进行评价，因此，我们
don't have a rating for that,
并没有这部电影的星级评价，
and Alice really did not
Alice 并不喜欢
like Nonstop Car Chases or
Nonstop Car Chases或者
Swords vs. Karate. And a different user
Swords vs. Karate. 另一个用户
Bob, user two, maybe rated
Bob,用户2，可能评级
a different set of movies, maybe
一些不同的电影，可能
she likes to Love at Last,
他喜欢Love at Last,
did not to watch Romance Forever,
并没有看过Romance Forever,
just have a rating of 4, a 0,
仅仅评了一个4星，一个0星，
a 0, and maybe our 3rd user,
可能第三个用户，
rates this 0, did not watch
评价它为0星，并没有看过
that one, 0, 5, 5, and, you know, let's just
那部电影，0, 5, 5,你知道的，让我们仅仅
fill in some of the numbers.
用一些数字填满。
And so just to introduce a
下面介绍一些
bit of notation, this notation
符号，这些符号
that we'll be using throughout, I'm going
我们将一直使用，我将
to use NU to denote the number of users.
用NU表示用户的数量。
So in this example, NU will be equal to 4.
因此，在这个例子中，NU=4。
So the u-subscript stands for
u的下标表示
users and Nm,
用户数，Nm
going to use to denote the number
用来表示电影的数量，
of movies, so here I have five movies
这里我有5部电影，
so Nm equals equals 5.
因此Nm=5.
And you know for this example, I have
这个例子你知道的，
for this example, I have loosely
我有
3 maybe romantic or
3部浪漫或
romantic comedy movies and 2
浪漫喜剧和2部
action movies and you know, if
动作片，
you look at this small example, it
你看这个小例子，它
looks like Alice and Bob are
看起来像是Alice和 Bob
giving high ratings to these
评了高星级给这些
romantic comedies or movies
浪漫喜剧或者关于爱情的电影，
about love, and giving very
给动作片非常
low ratings about the action
低的评价，
movies, and for Carol and Dave, it's the opposite, right?
Carol 和 Dave，他们的评价是相反的，对吗？
Carol and Dave, users three
Carol 和 Dave，用户3和4，
and four, really like the
喜欢
action movies and give them
动作片并给它们
high ratings, but don't like
高星级，但是不喜欢
the romance and love-
浪漫剧和
type movies as much.
爱情剧。
Specifically, in the recommender system
尤其在推荐系统问题中，
problem, we are given the following data.
我们给定下面数据，
Our data comprises the following:
我们的数据组成如下：
we have these values r(i, j), and
我们有值r(i, j),
r(i, j) is 1 if user
r(i, j)=1，如果用户
J has rated movie I.
j给电影i进行了评价。
So our users rate only
因此，用户仅仅给
some of the movies, and so,
某些电影评价，诸如此类。
you know, we don't have
你知道，我们没有
ratings for those movies.
对这些电影进行评价。
And whenever r(i, j) is equal
r(i, j)等于1，仅当
to 1, whenever user j has
用户j
rated movie i, we also
给电影i进行了评价。我们也
get this number y(i, j),
得到值y(i, j)，
which is the rating given by
它是用户j给电影i的评级。
user j to movie i. And
so, y(i, j) would be
因此，y(i, j)是一个
a number from zero to
从0到5的数字，
five, depending on the star
依赖星级评定，
rating, zero to five
用户给
stars that user gave that particular movie.
特定电影评价0到5，五个星级。
So, the recommender system problem
因此，推荐系统问题
is given this data
给出了这个数据
that has give these r(i, j)'s
这些r(i, j)和
and the y(i, j)'s to look
y(i, j)数据，
through the data and
浏览数据
look at all the movie ratings that
查找所有未被评价的电影，
are missing and to try
并试图
to predict what these values
预测这些电影的评价星级。
of the question marks should be.
In the particular example, I have
在这个特殊的例子中，我有
a very small number of movies
非常少的电影数量
and a very small number of users
和用户数量，
and so most users have rated most
因此，大多数用户都对大多数电影进行了评价。
movies but in the realistic
但在现实情况中，
settings your users each
of your users may have rated
每个用户可能仅评价
only a minuscule fraction of your
你的一部分电影，
movies but looking at this
但看这些数据，
data, you know, if Alice and Bob
你知道的，如果Alice和Bob
both like the romantic movies
都喜欢浪漫剧
maybe we think that Alice would have given this a five.
我们可能认为Alice将给电影评价5星。
Maybe we think Bob would have
Bob或许给电影评价
given this a 4.5
4.5星
or some high value, as we
或更高的星级，
think maybe Carol and Dave
Carol和Dave
were doing these very low ratings.
将给浪漫剧非常低的评价。
And Dave, well, if Dave really likes action movies,
如果Dave真的喜欢动作片，
maybe he would have given
他可能给
Swords and Karate a 4
Swords and Karate评价4星
rating or maybe a 5 rating, okay?
或者5星。
And so, our job in developing
因此，如果我们想开发
a recommender system is to
一个推荐系统，
come up with a learning
那我们的工作是想出一个学习算法，
algorithm that can automatically
一个能自动
go fill in these missing values
为我们填补这些缺失值的算法，
for us so that we
因此，我们
can look at, say, the
可以看看，
movies that the user has
该用户还没有看
not yet watched, and recommend
电影，并推荐
new movies to that user to watch.
新电影给该用户看。
You try to predict what else might be interesting to a user.
你试图预测一个用户感兴趣的内容。
So that's the formalism of the recommender system problem.
因此，这是推荐系统问题的形式主义。
In the next video we'll start
下一段视频我们将
to develop a learning algorithm to address this problem.
开发一个学习算法解决这个问题。